--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制：玄子 　字幕调校：我爱罗　招募Q号：76846146
片名：愤怒的葡萄   原著约翰·斯坦贝克
主演：亨利·方达 简·达维尔 多利丝·波顿 查利·格拉普文
联合制片/编剧：南奈利·约翰逊
导演：约翰·福特
- When'll you be back, Roy? - Oh, in a couple of weeks.
- 你什么时候回来？ - 一两个礼拜吧
Don't do nothing you wouldn't want me to hear about.
别做出对不起我的事
- Well, so long. - So long.
- 好的 再见 - 再见
How about a lift, mister?
搭个便车可以吗？
- Can't you see that sticker? - Sure, l see it.
- 你没看见牌子吗？ - 看见了
车主敬告严禁载客
But a good guy don't pay no attention to what some heel makes him stick on his truck.
可好心人不会理会牌子说什么
Well, scrunch down on the running board till we get around the bend.
先在踏板上猫一下 上路后再上来
- Going far? - No, just a couple of miles.
- 很远吗？ - 几里而已
l'd have walked her if my dogs wasn't pooped out.
我的狗没死的话我会走回去的
- Looking for ajob? - No. My old man's got a place.
- 在找工作？ - 不 我父亲有四十亩田
40 acres. He's a sharecropper, but we've been there a long while.
他是佃农 不过我们已经在这儿很久了
- Been doing ajob? - Yeah.
- 一直在务农？ - 对
l seen your hands. You been swinging a pick or a sledge.
我看过你的手 似乎经常抡大锤
That's what makes them shiny. l notice things like that all the time.
都磨光了 我很注意这种小的细节
Got a trade?
有买卖吗？
- Why don't you get at it, buddy? - Get at what?
- 为什么不直说？ - 说什么？
You know. You been goin' over me since l got in. Why don't you ask where l've been?
你上车就对我打听个不停 何不直接问我
l don't stick my nose in nobody's business. l stay in my own yard.
我不过问别人的事
That big nose of yours been goin' over me like a sheep in a vegetable patch.
我只管自扫门前雪 你已经打听得够多了
l ain't keepin' it secret. l've been in the penitentiary. Been there four years.
我直说好了 我蹲了四年牢
- Anything else? - You ain't gotta get sore.
- 还想知道什么吗？ - 别发火
- Ask me anything. - l didn't mean nothing.
- 再问啊 - 我没有恶意
Me neither. l'm just trying to get along without shovin' anybody, that's all.
我也是 我也只想和善待人
See that road ahead? That's where l get out.
看到前面的路了吗？我在那儿下车
You're about to bust a gut to know what l done, ain't you?
你想知道我为什么坐牢对吧？
l ain't a guy to let you down.
我不会扫你的兴
Homicide.
凶杀案
Hmm, He's my saviour
他是我的救星？
Hmm, my saviour
我的救星？
Hmm, my saviour now
- Howdy, friend. - Howdy.
- 你好 伙计 - 你好
Ain't you young Tom Joad, old Tom's boy?
你不是老乔德的孩子吗？
Yeah. l'm on my way home now.
对 我正要回家
Well, l do declare.
我就说
l baptised you, son.
你是我施洗的
Ain't you the preacher?
你是牧师？
Used to be.Not no more.
以前是 不再是了
l lost the call.
我失去恩宠了
But, boy, l sure used to have it.
以前不是如此
l used to get an irrigation ditch so full of repented sinners
以往我的圣水是多么充足
l'd pretty near drown half of 'em.
简直可以把人淹死
But not no more.
如今不行了
l lost the spirit.
我失去了圣灵
l got nothing to preach about no more, that's all.
我无法再传道了
l ain't so sure of things.
对事情不敢肯定
l remember you preaching a sermon
我记得你传教时…
walking around on your hands, shoutin' your head off.
全神贯注 声嘶力竭的样子
Yeah, l remember.Went pretty good that way.
我也记得 那时真好
But that was nothin'.
可那算不上什么
l preached a whole sermon once straddling the ridge pole of a barn.
有一次我还在牲口棚的横梁上布道
Like this.
像这样
- Did you see that one? - No.
- 那次你在吗？ - 不在
You didn't?
没有？
Well, it's all gone anyway.
反正一切都过去了
You should have got yourself a wife.
你应该讨个老婆
Why, at my meetings, l used to get the girls a-glory-shoutin' till they about passed out.
我在布道时常把女孩说得给昏过去
Then l'd go to comfort 'em.
然后我趁势安慰她们
l'd always end up by loving 'em.
最后总是爱上她们
l'd feel bad and pray and pray, but it didn't do no good.
我觉得有罪 一再祷告 可是无济于事
Next time do it again.
下一次又再犯
l figured l just wasn't worth saving.
我大概是无可救药了
Pa always says you was never cut out for no preacher.
爸说你根本不是牧师的料
l never let one get by me if l could catch her. Have a snort?
如果我找到女人才不放她走.来一口吗？
But you wasn't a preacher. A girl was just a girl to you.
可是你不是牧师
女人在你而言只是女人
To me they's holy vessels.
对我而言她们是圣器
l was saving their souls.
我在拯救她们的灵魂
l asked myself, what is this here called holy spirit?
我自问：什么是圣灵？
Maybe that's love.
或许就是爱
Why, l love everybody so much l'm fit to burst sometimes.
我太爱世人
所以有时难免按捺不住
So... maybe there ain't no sin and there ain't no virtue.
或许世上并无罪恶 也无善德
lt's just what people does.
有的只是人的行为
Some things folks do is nice and some ain't so nice.
有的人做得好 有的人不太好
And that's all any man's got a right to say.
只能这么说
Of course, l'll say a grace if somebody sets out the food.
如果有人布施 我会赞美他
But my heart ain't in it.
但我并非真心
- Nice drinkin' liQuor. - Ought to be. lt's factory liQuor. Cost a buck.
- 好酒 - 那当然 花了一块钱买的
- You been out travelling around? - Ain't you heard? lt's been in the papers.
你一直在旅行？
你没听说吗？报上有报
- No, l never. What? - l've been in the penitentiary for four years.
- 没有 什么？ - 我被关了四年
Excuse me for asking.
我不该问的
l don't mind no more. l'd do what l done again.
我不在乎了 换成现在我还会那么作
Killed a guy in a dance hall.
我在舞厅杀了一个人
We was drunk. He got a knife in me and l laid him out with a shovel.
我们醉了 他拿刀对着我
- Knocked his head plumb to sQuash. - You ain't ashamed?
我用铁锹把他打倒 把头打烂了
No. He had a knife in me. That's why they only gave me seven years.
- 你不觉的可耻？ - 他拿刀对着我
l got out in four. Parole.
所以才判了七年 我被假释了
- Ain't seen your folks since? - No, but l aim to before sundown.
- 四年来见过家人吗 - 没 但马上就能
And l'm gettin' excited about it too.
- 觉得有点兴兴 - 你上哪儿去？
- Which way are you goin'? - Oh, it don't matter.
无所谓
Ever since l lost the spirit, looks like l'd just as soon go one way as the other.
失去圣灵后
l'll go your way.
我便四处游荡
我跟着你好了
Maybe Ma will have pork for supper.
或许妈会煮猪肉来吃
l ain't had pork but four times in four years. Every Christmas.
我四年来只吃了四次猪肉 每年圣诞吃一次
l'll be glad to see your pa.
能见到你老爸真好
Last time l seen him was at a baptising.
上次是在施洗时看见他的
He had one of the biggest doses of the holy spirit l ever seen.
他身上充满了圣灵
Got to jumping over bushes. Howlin' like a dog-wolf at moon-time.
起灵时还跳过树从 像只满月的狼一样大叫
Finally, he picks himself out a bush big as a piano
最后他拾起一支大木棍
and he lets out a sQuawk and takes a run at that bush.
大叫一声又跳向树从
Well, he cleared her.
然后他退灵了
But he bust his leg snap in two doing it.
却也摔伤了腿
There was a travelling dentist and he set her and l gave her a praying over, but...
幸好路过的牙医替他接上
我也为他祈祷
there wasn't no more holy spirit left in your pa after that.
可是自此他身上就没有生灵了
- Listen. That wind's fixing to do something. - Sure it is.
听？这阵风恐怕大有来头
Always is this time of year.
当然 每年此时都是如此
Ma?
妈？
Pa?
爸？
Ma?
妈？
Ain't nobody here.
没人在家
- Something's happened. - You got a match?
- 出事了 - 有火柴吗？
They're all gone or dead.
他们不是走了就是死了
- They never wrote you nothing? - No. They wasn't people to write.
- 他们没写信给你吗 - 没 他们不识字
lt's Ma's. She had 'em for years.
妈的老靴子
Used to be mine. l gave it to Grandpa when l went away.
我的帽子 我走时送给祖父的
You reckon they're dead?
你想他们死了吗？
l never heard nothing about it.
没听说过有这回事
(man) Tommy?
汤姆？
Muley.
莫里
- Where's my folks, Muley? - Why, they gone.
- 我的家人呢？ - 他们走了
l know they're gone, but where are they gone?
我知道 上哪儿去了
lt's Muley Graves. You remember the preacher, don't you?
莫里 你认识牧师吧？
- l ain't no preacher any more. - All right. You remember the man?
- 我不再是牧师了 - 好 你认得他吧
- Glad to see you again. - Now, where are my folks?
- 幸会 - 我家人呢？
They gone. They gone to your Uncle John's.
走了 到你约翰叔叔那里去了
The whole crowd of 'em. Two weeks ago.
半月前全走了
But they can't stay there, cos John's got his notice to get off.
可是那儿也待不久 因为约翰也要被赶走了
What happened? How come they gotta get off?
出了什么事？为何要走？
We lived here 50 years, same place.
我们在这里住了50年
Everybody's gotta get off. Everybody's leaving. Going out to California.
所有人都得走 到加州去
Your folks, my folks, everybody's folks.
你家人 我家人 所有人
Everybody except me. l ain't getting off!
除了我之外 我才不走
- Who done it? - Listen.
- 谁干的？ - 听
That's some of what done it. The dusters. They started it, anyways.
它是元凶 风沙又再吹了
Blowin' like this year after year.
像这样年复一年
Blowin' the land away. Blowin' the crops away!
把土地吹走 把粮食吹走
Blowin' us away now.
现在又要把我们吹走
Are you crazy?
你疯了？
Some say l am. You wanna hear how it happened?
有人说我是疯了 想知道一切经过吗
That's what l'm asking you, ain't it?
我问的正是此事
Well... the way it happens,
事情经过是…
the way it happened to me...
在我而言…
A man come one day...
有一天来了一个人
After what them dusters done to the land, the tenant system don't work no more.
在风沙侵害了土地后佃农制已维持不下去了
They don't break even, much less show profit.
连度日都难 更别提利润
One man and a tractor can handle 12 or 14 of these places.
一人一部拖拉机就可以种12到14户的土地
You just pay him a wage and take all the crop.
只要付够工钱就行
Yeah, but we couldn't do on any less than what our share is now.
可是我们将一无所有
The children ain't getting enough to eat as it is. And they're so ragged,
小孩会没饭吃 他们又爱玩…
we'd be ashamed if everybody else's children wasn't the same.
别的小孩吃的饱我们会丢脸的
l can't help that. l got my orders. They told me to tell you to get off.
我也无能为力 我是奉命行事 我奉命叫你们搬走
- That's what l'm tellin' you. - You mean get off my own land?
- 我只能把话传到 - 叫我们离开自己的土地？
- Don't go to blaming me. lt ain't my fault. - Whose fault is it?
- 别怪我 又不是我的错 - 那是谁的错？
You know who owns the land. Shawnee Land and Cattle Company.
你知道地主是谁 夏尼畜牧公司
- Who's Shawnee Land and Cattle Company? - Nobody. lt's a company.
- 谁是夏尼畜牧公司 - 不是人 是公司
They got a president. They got somebody who knows what a shotgun's for!
他们有老板吧？他应该知道枪是作什么用的
Oh, son, it ain't his fault because the bank tells him what to do.
也不是他的错 是银行下的命令
- All right. Where's the bank? - Tulsa. What's the use of picking on him?
- 好 银行在哪儿？- 你找到了又有什么用呢
He ain't nothing but the manager. He's half crazy trying to keep up with his orders.
他只是经理 费尽心思地执行东部传达的命令
- Then who do we shoot? - Brother, l don't know.
- 我们该找谁算帐？ - 我不知道
lf l did, l'd tell you. l just don't know who's to blame.
如果知道我会告诉你的 我实在不知道该怪谁
l'm right here to tell you, mister: there ain't nobody gonna push me off my land!
谁也别想赶走我
My grandpa took up this land 70 years ago!
我祖父七十年前在此落户
My pa was born here. We was all born on it! And some of us was killed on it!
我老爸在此地出生 有人在这里被杀
And some of us... died on it.
有人死在这里
That's what makes it our'n.
所以它是我们的土地
Being born on it,
生在这儿…
and workin' on it...
耕作在这儿…
and dying... dying on it!
死在这儿
And not no piece of paper with writing on it...
不能任由一纸公文就…
Well, what happened?
怎么回事？
They come. They come and pushed me off.
他们来了 他们来赶我走
- They come with the cats. - The what?
- 他们带来了"毛虫" - 什么？
The cats, the caterpillar tractors.
"毛虫" 就是推土机
And for every one of 'em, there was ten, 15 families thrown right out of their homes.
每部机器至少压平了十到十五户家庭的土地
100 folks. And no place to live but on the road.
上百个家庭因此无家可归
The Rances, the Peterses, the Perrys, the Joadses...
兰斯家 彼得家 贝里家 乔德家
One right after the other, they got thrown out.
一个接一个被赶走
Half the folks you and me know thrown right out into the road.
我们认识的家庭半数以上被赶出家门
The one that got me come about a month ago.
一个月前他们来到我家
Go on back!
滚回去
Go on back! l'm warning you! Go on back!
我警告你 滚回去
You come any closer and l'm gonna blow you right out of that cat!
你再过来我就开枪了
l told you!
我说真的
- You're Joe Davis' boy. - l don't like for nobody to draw a bead on me.
- 你是乔·戴维斯的儿子 - 我也不想被人拔枪相向
Then what are you doing this for? Against your own people.
那你为何开那机器对付自己人？
Three dollars a day, that's what l'm doing it for.
为了一天赚三块钱
l got two little kids at home. My wife. My wife's mother. Them folks gotta eat.
我有两个小孩 太太 岳母要养活
First and only, l think about my folks
我得为自己家人着想
What happens to others is their own lookout.
其他人的事我管不了
Yeah, but you don't understand, son. This is my land!
你不知道吗？这是我的土地
Used to be. lt's the company's now.
以前是 现在是公司的了
Have it your own way, son. Butjust as sure as you touch my house with that cat,
随你怎么说 可是只要你敢动我的房子
l'm gonna blow you plumb to kingdom come!
我就打烂你的脑袋
You ain't gonna blow nobody nowhere! First place, they'd hang you and you know it.
你谁也奈何不了 首先 他们会吊死你
lt wouldn't be two days before they'd send a guy to take my place.
过两天又会有人过来
Now go on! Get outta the way!
快让开
What was the use? He was right.
有什么用？他是对的
There wasn't a thing in the world l could do about it.
我无能为力
lt's just... it don't seem possible just getting throwed off like that.
似乎不可思议 一切就这样毁掉了
The rest of my family set out for the West.
我的家人已往西去了
There wasn't nothing to eat, but... l couldn't leave. Something just wouldn't let me.
这儿没吃的 可是我不能走 有什么东西牵扯着我
So now l just wander around and sleep wherever l am.
现在我只好四处为家
l used to tell myself that l was looking out for things
我常告诉自己我在照顾一切
so that when the folks come back, everything would be all right.
等家人回来 一切都会好的
But l knowed it wasn't true.
可我知道我在自欺欺人
There ain't nothin' to look out for.
这儿没什么好照料的了
And there ain't nobody ever coming back.
不会有人回来了
They're gone!
他们走了
And me...
而我
l'm just an old graveyard ghost.
只是个老游魂
That's all in the world l am.
我就是个老游魂
Do you think l'm touched?
我是否有圣灵俯身？
No.
没有
You're lonely, but...
你很孤独 但…
you ain't touched.
没有
Well, it don't matter. lf l'm touched, l'm touched and that's all there is to it.
没关系 圣灵附不附身都无所谓
The thing l don't understand is my folks taking it. Like Ma.
我实在不明白我家人如何忍得下
l seen her nearly beat a pedlar to death with a live chicken.
拿我妈说 她用一只活难差点打死一小贩
She aimed to go with an axe in the other hand, got mixed up
她本打算用另一只手中的斧头
forgot which was which.
可是她搞混了
When she got through with that pedlar, all she had left was two chicken legs.
等小贩走后她手上只剩下两条难腿
Just a...
一个…
Just a plain old graveyard ghost.
一个坟场老游魂
That's all.
如此而已
She's settling.
风停了
What do you figure on doing?
打算怎么办？
lt's hard to say.
很难说
Stay here till morning, go to Uncle John's, l reckon.
待到天亮 再到叔叔那儿去吧
After that, l don't know.
再下去我也不知道
Listen.
听
That's them. Them lights.
他们来了 看他们的车灯
Come on. Come on. We gotta hide out.
快 我们得藏起来
Hide out for what? We ain't doing nothing.
藏什么 我们又没作坏事
You're trespassing. This ain't your land no more! That's the superintendent with a gun.
你侵入他人土地了 这已不是你的土地了 他们可都带了枪
- Come on! - Come on, Tom. You're on parole.
- 快走 汤姆 - 你还在假释期间
Muley!
莫里
All you gotta do is hide and watch.
藏起来看 不要作声
- Won't they come out here? - (chuckles) l don't think so.
- 他们不会过来吗？ - 应该不会
One came out once and l clipped him...
只要过来我就从后面
..from behind with a fence stake.
拿棍子给他一下
They ain't bothered since.
他们从此就不会找麻烦了
He ain't here.
他不在这儿
Anybody ever told me l'd be hiding out in my own place...
真没想到在自己家还要躲躲藏藏
Lord, make us grateful for what we are about to receive, for His sake. Amen.
主 请让我们为未来的遭受心存感激
l seen you. You ate during grace.
我看见你偷吃
Just one little dab. Just one teeny little old dab. That's all.
只有一小块 只是仅仅的一小块 就这些
- Ain't he messy though. - l seen him. Gobbling away like an old pig.
- 他真脏 - 像头猪一样
Why don't you keep your eyes shut during grace?
你为何不把眼闭上
What's it say again, Uncle John?
上面又说什么呢 约翰叔叔？
lt says, ''Plenty of work in California. 800 pickers wanted.''
加州有许多工作机会 需要800个采果工
Wait till l get to California. l'm gonna reach up and pick me an orange whenever l want it.
等我到了加州要随心所欲的摘橘子 葡萄
Or some grapes. Now-now-now, there's something l ain't never had enough of.
这些东西我永不嫌多
l'm gonna get me a whole big bunch of grapes off a bush
我要采一大串葡萄
and l'm gonna sQuash 'em all over my face and let the juice drain down off of my chin.
挤在脸上 让葡萄汁流到下巴
Praise the Lord for victory!
永远赞美上帝
Maybe l'll get me a whole washtub full of grapes
或许要弄一大箱葡萄
and just sit in 'em and scrounge around in 'em until they're all gone.
坐进箱里挤到它们全不见
l sure would like that. Yes, sir, l sure would like that.
我真希望这样 我真希望这样
Oh, thank God. Thank God.
感谢上帝
Tommy.
汤姆
Ma.
妈
You didn't bust out? You ain't gotta hide
你不是越狱吧？不用躲躲藏藏吧？
No, Ma. l'm paroled. l got my papers.
我获假释了 有证件
l was just scared we was going away without you and we'd never see each other again.
我真怕把你一个人丢下从此再也不能见面
l'd have found you, Ma.
我找到你们了
Muley told me what happened.
莫里把事情告诉我了
We going to California true?
真的要去加州？
We've gotta go, Tommy, but it's gonna be all right.
非去不可 不过会好起来的
l seen the handbills about how much work there is, and high wages too.
报道上说加州有许多工作 薪水也很高
There's something l gotta find out first, Tommy. Did they hurt you, son?
我得先弄清楚
- Did they hurt you and make you mean mad? - Mad, Ma?
- 他们伤害了你吗？是不是打得你疯了？- 疯？
- Sometimes they do. - No, Ma. l was at first, but not no more.
- 有时他们会这么干的 - 起初会 但后来就没有了
Sometimes they do something to you.
他们常如此
They hurt you and you get mad and then you get mean.
虐待你使你变得无情
And they hurt you again and you get meaner and meaner,
再虐待 你越来越无情
till you ain't no boy nor man any more, just a walking chunk of mean mad.
使你变得没有人性 变成行尸走肉或冷酷的疯子
- Did they hurt you that way, son? - No, Ma. Don't worry about that.
- 他们这样伤害你了吗？- 别乱操心了
Well, l...l don't want no mean son.
我不要无情的儿子
lt's Tommy. lt's Tommy back.
是汤姆汤姆回来了 汤姆
What did you do, son? Bust out?
你越狱了？
Tommy's out ofjail!
汤姆出狱了？
l... l knowed it! You couldn't keep him in. You can't keep a Joad in jail.
我就知道 牢房关不住他牢房关不住乔德家的人
l knowed it from the first.
我早就知道
Get out of my way! l told you so. l told you Tom would come bustin' out of thatjail
别挡着我我早就说过汤姆一定会越狱的
just like a bull through corral fence. You can't keep a Joad in jail.
就像公牛跃出畜栏 牢房关不住我家的人
- l didn't bust out. They paroled me. - l was that way myself.
- 我没越狱 是假释 - 我就是这样
- How are you, Uncle John? - Hello, Tommy. l'm feeling fine.
- 你好 叔叔 - 你好 汤姆 我很好
- How are you, Noah? - Fine, Tommy. Bust out?
- 你好 诺亚 - 你好 汤姆 越狱？
No, parole.
不 是假释
- Hello. - Tommy.
- 你好 - 汤姆
The jailbird's back! The jailbird's back!
牢鸟回来了
- Hiya, Al. - Hello, Tom.
- 你好 - 汤姆
- Did you bust out ofjail? - No, they paroled me.
- 越狱吗？ - 不 是假释
Rosasharn.
罗丝
Busted out.
越狱
That's Connie Rivers with her. They're married now.
她结婚了 这是她丈夫康尼
She's due now about three, four months.
她再有三四个月就要生了
She wasn't any more than a kid when l went up.
我走时她还是个孩子
- Hiya, Rosasharn. - How are you, Tom?
- 你好 罗丝 - 你好 汤姆
This is Connie, my husband.
这位是我丈夫康尼
- Did you... - No, parole.
- 你是不是… - 假释
Well, if this don't beat all. l see l'm going to be an uncle soon.
真是神奇 我快当舅舅了
Oh, you do not see.
不会的
- Look at her blush. Look at her blush. - Look at her blushing.
- 看她脸红了 看她脸红了 - 看她脸红了
Hey, Joad! John Joad.
乔德 约翰·乔德
- You ain't forgot, have you? - We ain't forgot.
- 你还没忘 - 没忘
- We'll be coming through here tomorrow. - l know.
- 我们明天一走就要来 - 我知道
We be out. We be out by sun-up.
到时我们就走 我们天亮就离开
- How did you get all this money? - Sold things. Chopped cotton. Even Grandpa.
- 你怎么弄到钱的？ - 卖东西 采棉花 祖父都下手了
Got us about $200 all told. Shucked out 75 for this here truck.
赚了200块 买车花了75块
Still got nearly 150 to set out on. l figure we ought to be able to make her on that.
还有125块路上用 应该够了
Easy. After all, they ain't but about 12 of us, is they?
小心点 一共有12个人
l reckon we better begin rousting them out if we aim to get out by daylight.
好 天亮就要离开这儿的话我们现在就叫大家上路吧
How about it, John? How you boys coming?
怎么样 约翰？你们也来吗？好
乔德被判入狱七年
Ma.
妈
l'm ready.
我好了
Rosasharn, honey. Wake up the children. We're fixing to leave.
罗丝 把小孩叫起来 要上路了
Ruthie. Winfield. Jump up now.
露西 文菲尔德 起床
- Where's Grandpa? Al, go get him. - l'm gonna get up front. Somebody help me.
- 爷爷呢？去找他 - 我要上去 帮帮忙
Wait.
等等
- Kids, you climb up on top first. - We're going to California!
- 小孩爬到上面去 - 我要去加利福尼亚了
Al's gonna drive, Ma. Sit with him and Grandma and we'll swap later.
艾尔开车 你们三个坐一起 稍后我们再换
Connie. Help Rosasharn up there alongside the kids.
我们去哪儿？康尼 帮罗丝照顾孩子
- Where's Grandpa? - Grandpa!
- 爷爷呢？ - 爷爷
Where he always is, probably.
他一定在老地方
Grandpa! Grandpa!
爷爷
Save him a place. John, you and Noah climb up and find a place.
留个位子 约翰 你们上去自己找个地方
Got to kind of keep her even all around.
注意保持车子平衡
- Think it'll hold? - lf it does, it'll be a miracle out of Scripture.
- 承受得住吗？- 受得住的话真是个奇迹
Ma. Pa.
妈 爸
Let go of me, goldurn you! Dang you!
放开我
Please. There's something the matter with him.
爷爷 怎么回事？
- Why don't you stand still! - There's something wrong with him.
- 站好 - 他怎么回事
- You let me alone, that's all. - That's all what?
- 我不去了 就这样 - 就怎样啊？
What's the matter, Grandpa?
怎么了 爷爷？
What's the matter? There's nothing the matter. l just...
怎么回事？没事
- l just ain't going, that's all. - What do you mean? We gotta go.
- 我不走了 - 什么意思 你不走？我们必须走
We got no place to stay.
这没地方住了
l ain't talking about you. l'm talking about me.
我不是说你 我是说我自己
l give her a good going over all last night and l'm staying.
我昨天好好想了想 决定留下来
But you can't do that, Grandpa. This here land's going under the tractor.
你不能这样 爷爷 这片土地上都是推土机
- We all got to get out. - All except me and l'm staying.
- 我们都得走 - 除了我 我要留下
- What about Grandma? - Take her with you!
- 奶奶呢？- 让她留下来陪你
Who'd cook for you, Grandpa? How are you gonna live?
谁给你做饭呢 奶奶？你怎么活下去呢？
Muley's living, ain't he? And l'm twice the man that Muley is.
莫里能行 我也能行 我比他强多了
Now, listen to me, Grandpa. Listen to me just a minute.
听着
And l ain't listening either.
我不听
l told you what l was gonna do and l don't give a hoot and a holler
我已经跟你说了我的决定
if there's oranges and grapes crowding a fella out of bed.
那儿的橘子和葡萄
l ain't going to California.
我不去加州
Goldurn! This is my country and l belong here.
这是我的土地 我属于这里
Yes, sir.
是的
lt's my dirt.
我的泥土
lt's no good, but it's...
这里土地不算好
it's mine, all mine.
但是我的 全是我的
Either we got to tie him up and throw him in the truck, or something. He can't stay here.
是不是要把他绑起来丢上车？ 他不能呆在这儿
No, can't tie him. Either we'll hurt him, or he'll get so mad, he'll hurt himself.
不能绑 否则不是我们弄伤他就是他弄伤自己
- Reckon we could get him drunk? - Ain't no whiskey, is there?
- 把他灌醉好了？ - 没有威士忌
Now, wait. There's a half a bottle of soothing syrup here.
还有半瓶蜜酒
Here. Used to put the children to sleep.
用来哄小孩睡觉的
- Don't taste bad. - There's coffee left. We can fix him a cup.
- 味道不差 - 还有点咖啡 帮他搞一杯
- That's right, douse some in it. - Better give him a good dose.
- 对 放一点 - 最好多放点
He's mighty muleheaded.
他很倔强
lf Muley...
如果莫里…
lf Muley can scramble along, l...
如果莫里能凑合下去
l guess l can.
我也能
l smell spareribs.
我闻到排骨的味道
Somebody's been eating spareribs. How come l ain't got none?
有人在吃排骨 为什么我没有？
Well, l got some saved for you, Grandpa. Got some warming now.
我留了一些给你 正在热
But here's a cup of coffee for you first.
先喝杯咖啡
Get me a mess of spareribs.
留点排骨给我
l want a great big mess of spareribs.
我要一大块猪排
- l'm... l'm hungry. - Why, sure you're hungry.
- 我饿了 - 你当然饿
l... sure do like spareribs.
我真喜欢猪排
- Get up there, Noah. - Put his feet in there first, Tom.
- 快上去 诺亚 - 先把脚放上去 汤姆
Easy, now. Easy!
帮忙 慢 慢
Better throw something over him so he won't get sunstruck.
最好给他盖点什么 省得他中暑
Everything all set now? All right, let her go, Al.
好了吗？ 好了 上路吧 艾尔
Get aboard, Ma.
上车 妈
- Well, goodbye and good luck. - Hold her, Al.
- 一路顺风 - 扶住她
Ain't you goin' with us?
你不一起走吗？
l'd like to.
我想去
There's something going on out there in the West and l'd like to try and learn what it is.
我想去西部看个究竟
lf you feel you've got the room.
如果还有位子
Plenty of room. Get on.
位子多的是 上来
- Let her go, Al! - California, here we come!
- 上来 凯西走吧 艾尔 - 我们来了 加州
Ain't you gonna look back, Ma? Give the old place a last look?
你不回头看一眼吗？看看我们的老家
We're going to California, ain't we? All right then, let's go to California.
我们要去加州 那就一路往加州前进
That don't sound like you. You never was like that before.
这不像你的口气 妈 你从没有这样过
l never had my house pushed over before.
我的家也从来没有被人推倒过
Never had my family stuck out on the road.
我的家人从没有无家可归过
Never had to lose everything l had in life.
我一生从未失去过什么
热鱼餐配玉米饼
撤卡塔城界
俄克拉荷马城界
卡车站：补胎充气
- lt's gonna be all right, Grandpa. - l ain't going.
- 不会有事的 爷爷 - 我不去…
l ain't going. l ain't going.
我不去
l ain't going.
lt's all right, Grandpa.
没事的 爷爷
You're just tired, that's all.
你累了而已
That's it.
对
Just tired.
累了
Just...
只是…
tired.
累了
''This here is William James Joad. Died of a stroke, old, old man.''
威廉姆·詹姆斯·乔德死于中风 葬于此地 一位老人
''His folks buried him because they got no money to pay for funeral...s.''
家人贫寒 无力付丧葬费 因此将他葬在此地
''Nobody killed him. Just a stroke and he died.''
非他杀 为中风而死
l figure best we leave something like this on him,
最好留下张纸条
'lest somebody digs him up and makes out he was killed.
免得有人掘出尸体误认是他杀
Looks like a lot of times the government's got more interest in a dead man than a live one.
似乎政府较关心死人而忽视了活人
Not be so lonesome, knowing his name's there with him.
他的名字留在这里 他不会寂寞的
Notjust an old fella lonesome underground.
他不是一个埋身地下的无名老人
Would you say a few words, Casy?
凯西 你要不要说几句话？
l ain't a preacher no more, you know.
我已不是牧师了
We know, but ain't none of our folks ever been buried without a few words.
可是我家人下葬没有不经祷告的
l'll say 'em, make it short.
我简要祈祷几句好了
This here old man just...
人活了一生
lived a life and just died out of it.
不久前死去此
l don't know whether he was good or bad.
我不敢断言其一生善恶
lt don't matter much.
这也无关紧要
Heard a fella say a poem once.
诗人曾说
And he says, ''All that lives is holy.''
所有生命都是神圣的
Well, l wouldn't pray just for an old man that's dead,
我不只是为死去的老人祈祷
cos he's all right.
他已安息于地下
lf l was to pray, l'd pray for folks that's alive and don't know which way to turn.
我要为活人祈祷 因为他们不知何去何从
Grandpa here...
长眠地下的老人…
he ain't got no more trouble like that.
已经免了这个麻烦
He's got his job all cut out for him, so cover him up and let him get to it.
他已了却一生责任 收容他 让他安息吧
出售淡水 15分一加仑
此处露营 每晚50分
l'm going down the road feeling bad
我走在路上 满腹惆怅
l'm going down the road feeling bad, oh lordy
我走在路上 满腹惆怅 我的上帝
l ain't going to be treated this way
我不想忍受这样的冷遇
They fed me on corn bread and beans
他们给我吃玉米面包和碗豆
Gosh, Connie sure sings pretty, don't he?
天哪 康尼唱的真不错
Oh lordy
我的上帝
l ain't going to be treated this way
我不想忍受这样的冷遇
- That's my son-in-law. - Sings real nice. What state you all from?
- 这是我女婿 - 歌喉真棒 你们从哪儿来？
Oklahoma. Had us a farm there, sharecropping.
俄克拉荷马 我们是那儿的佃农 本来有间农场
We're from Arkansas.
我们从阿肯色州来
Had me a store there. Kind of a general notions store.
以前开杂货店
When the farms went, the stores went too.
农场关闭了 店也跟着倒闭
l had as nice a little store as you ever saw.
我那间店有你想不出的那么好
l sure did hate to give it up.
真舍不得
Well, you can't tell.
世事难料
l figure when we get out there and get work,
或许等找到工作
maybe get us a piece of growing land near water, it might not be so bad at that.
有块近水源的土地 生活也会不错
That's right. Paying good wages, l hear.
对 听说那里工资金挺高
- We can all get work. - Can't be no worse than home.
我们都能找到工 总比家里好
You all must have a pot of money.
你们很有钱吧
No, we ain't got no money, but there's plenty of us to work and we're all good men.
没钱 可是我们人手多 个个都能干
Get good wages out there and put it all together and we'll be all right.
把工资金凑起来生活便会好转
Good wages, eh? Picking oranges and peaches?
高工资金？靠采果吗？
- Well, we aim to take whatever they got. - What's so funny about that?
- 有什么我们就采什么？ - 有什么好笑的？
What's so funny about it? l've just been out there.
有什么好笑的？我刚从哪儿回来
l've been and seen it. l'm going back and starve
亲身经历过 就这样空着肚子回来
because l'd rather starve all over at once.
我宁肯一下子饿死
What do you think you're talking about? l got a handbill says they're paying good wages.
你说什么？这里有张传单说那里工资金很高
l seen in the papers they need pickers.
报纸上说他们急需采果工
All right, go on. Nobody's stopping you.
那您自便 没人拦着您
- Yeah, but what about this? - l ain't gonna rile you. Go on.
- 你什么意思？ - 我没打算跟你搅混
Wait a minute, buddy. You just done some jackassin'. You can't shut up now.
等等 你说了傻话 现在想住口来不及了
lt says they need 800 pickers.
传单说他们需要800采果工
You laugh and say they don't. Which one's the liar?
你嘲笑说没这回事 谁在撒谎？
- How many of you all got them handbills? - l got one.
- 都有谁拿到了这张传单？ - 我有
- l got one. - We all got one.
- 我也有 - 我们都有
- What does that prove? - There you are. Same yellow handbill.
- 这说明什么？ - 清一色的黄色传单
800 pickers wanted.
"招募800采果工"
All right, the man wants 800 men. So he prints 5,000 handbills
倘若需要800个采果工他会印发5000份传单
and maybe 20,000 people see 'em.
两万人会看到这份传单
And maybe two or 3,000 people start west on account of that handbill.
两三千人因为这张传单赶往西部
Two or 3,000 people that are crazy with worry
两三千饥寒交迫的人
heading out for 800 jobs. Now, does that make sense?
赶往西部抢夺800个工作机会 明白了吗？
Say, what are you, a troublemaker
你是谁？捣乱分子？
You sure you ain't one of them labour fakes?
你难道也是捏造消息的人？
l... l swear l ain't, mister.
我发誓我不是
Don't you go around here trying to stir up any trouble.
那就别到处煽风点火
l tried to tell you folks what it took me a year to find out.
我只想告诉大家我用一年才发现的事实
Took two kids dead. Took my wife dead to show me. But nobody could tell me neither.
我的妻儿都因此死去 没人肯告诉我
l can't tell you about them little fellows laying in the tent
我可怜的孩子躺在帐蓬里
with their bellies swelled out
肚皮肿胀
and just skin over their bones.
瘦骨嶙峋
Shivering and whining like pups.
瑟瑟发抖 像幼崽一样呜呜着
And me running around looking for work.
我四处找活儿干
Not for money. Not for wages.
不是为钱 不是为工资金
Just for a cup of flour and a spoon of lard.
就为了一把面粉 一块猪油
Then the coroner come.
验尸官来了
''Them children died of heart failure,'' he said. He put it down in his paper.
他在报告中写道："孩子们死于心脏病"
Heart failure?
心脏病？
And their little bellies stuck out like a pig bladder.
他们的肚皮明明肿得像猪泡
Well, it's late. l got to get some sleep.
我们得去睡觉了
Well...
好
Good night, folks.
晚安
Suppose he's telling the truth, that fella?
他说的是事实吧？
He's telling the truth.
对
The truth for him.
不过只是对他而言的事实
He wasn't making it up.
他没有捏造
Was it the truth for us?
他说的是实话吗？
l don't know.
我不知道
佩科斯河
新墨西哥
l got to get out, l tell you.
我要出去
l gotta get out now.
- You folks aim to buy anything? - We want some gas, mister.
- 你们要买什么吗？ - 汽油 先生
- Got any money? - What do you think? We're begging?
- 带钱了吗？ - 难道我们乞讨不成？
- l just asked, that's all. - Well, ask right. You ain't talking to bums.
- 我只是问问而已 - 好 我们不是讨饭的
All in the world l done was ask.
我只是问问而已
- What kind of pie you got? - Banana, pineapple, chocolate and apple.
- 这里有什么派？- 波萝 香蕉 巧克力和苹果派
Cut me a hunk of that banana cream and a cup ofjava.
来块香蕉乳酪 一杯爪哇咖啡
- Make it two. - Two it is.
- 两杯 - 马上就来
Seen any good etchings lately, Bill?
最近有没有见到什么好画 比尔？
Well, this one ain't bad. A little kid comes late for school and the teacher says...
有张不错的 有个小孩上学迟到了 老师说
Cheese it.
停停
Could you see your way clear to sell us a loaf of bread, ma'am?
能卖给我们一块面包吗？
This ain't a grocery store. We got bread to make sandwiches.
这里不是杂货店 我们的面包要做三明治
l know, ma'am. Only, it's for an old lady.
我知道 我们有位没牙的老太太
No teeth. Got to soften it with water so she can chew it, and she's hungry.
必须用水泡了才能吃 她饿了
Why don't you buy a sandwich? We got nice ones.
买个三明治不行吗？我们的三明治很好吃
Well, l sure would like to do that, ma'am. But the fact is, we ain't got but a dime for it.
我也想买 可我们没那个钱
lt's all figured out - l mean for the trip.
我们的钱全都为这次旅程计划好了
You can't buy no loaf of bread for a dime. We only got 15-cent loaves.
一角买不到面包 我们只有15美分的
- Give him the bread. - We'll run out before the bread truck comes!
- 把面包给他 - 面包车来之前我们就没了
All right, then we run out!
没就没
This here's a 15-cent loaf.
这是15美分的面包
Well, would you... could you see your way to cutting off ten cents worth?
你能不能…能不能切一角的分量？
- Give him the loaf. - No, sir. We wanna buy ten cents worth.
- 给他 - 不行 先生 我们只想买一角的面包
Go on, it's yesterday's bread.
去吧 反正是昨天的面包
Go ahead. Bert says to take it.
拿去吧 伯特说让你们拿去
Well, it may sound funny, being so tight, but we got 1,000 miles to go
好 经济这么紧张听起来可笑 但我们有1000英里的路要走
and we don't know if we'll make it.
还不知道能不能到达
ls them penny candies, ma'am?
这些糖是卖一分一块的吗？
- Which ones? - There, them stripy ones.
- 哪些？ - 带条纹那些
Oh, them.
噢 它们啊
Well... no.
不是
- Them's two for a penny. - Give us two then, ma'am.
- 一分两只 - 给我们两只好了
Go on, take 'em, take 'em.
去 拿着
Thank you, ma'am.
谢谢 太太
- Them ain't two-for-a-cent candy. - What's it to you?
- 那些糖不是卖一分两块的 - 关你什么事？
- Them's a-nickel-apiece candy. - We better get going. We're dropping time.
- 那些是卖五分一块的 - 我们走吧 时间不多了
- So long. - Wait a minute, you got change coming.
- 再见 - 等等 有零钱找给你
What's it to you?
留给你吧
Bert.
伯特
Look.
看看
Truck drivers.
不愧是卡车司机
您正在离开新墨西哥 欢迎再来
亚利桑那州欢迎您
国家检查站：牲畜检查站
- Where you going? - California.
- 你们去哪儿？ - 加州
- How long you plan to be in Arizona? - No longer than to get across.
- 打算在亚利桑那呆多久？ - 只是路过而已
- Got any plants? - No, no plants.
- 有植物吗？ - 没有
- OK, go ahead, but keep moving. - We aim to.
- 好 继续 不要停下 - 我们本来就打算一直前进
亚利桑那州：威尔罗杰斯公路
亚利桑那州：科罗拉多河
Well, there she is, folks. The land of milk and honey.
那里就是了 牛奶和蜂蜜之地
California.
加利福尼亚
Well, if that's what we came out here for...
我们大老远就为了这个
Connie, maybe it's nice on the other side
康尼 另一面可能会漂亮很多
Them picture postcards, they was real pretty.
记得那些漂亮的明信片吗？
There, Grandma. There's California.
奶奶 这就是加州
Let's get going. She don't look so tough to me, eh, John?
我们走吧 她对我并不像看着那样坏 是吧 约翰
Well, l don't know.
我不知道
Hold on!
坐好
亚利桑那州
千针林欢迎您来到加利福尼亚
- Ain't too cold, is she, Tom? - No, it's fine when you get in, Pa.
- 水不太凉吧 汤姆？ - 不凉 下来就好了 爸
Come on, John. Let's give her a whirl.
来 约翰 我们下去洗一洗
This is supposed to be good for you, John.
这对你的身体有好处 爸
- Come on, Pa, before she floats away. - Here we come.
- 来吧 爸爸 别让水都流光了 - 来了
- You people got a lot of nerve. - What do you mean?
- 你们真有股儿劲 - 什么意思？
- Crossing the desert in ajalopy like this. - You been across?
- 开这么一辆破车横穿沙莫 - 你穿过？
Sure, plenty. But never in no wreck like that.
从没开过这么破的车
lf we break down, maybe somebody'd give us a hand.
车坏了的话 可能会有人帮忙
Well, maybe, but l'd hate to be doing it. Takes more nerve than l got.
可能 但我讨厌帮忙 我没那个胆量
Don't take no nerve to do something, ain't nothing else you can do. Hope she holds.
不是胆量的问题 是没的选择 但愿它撑的住
Grandpa.
祖父
l want Grandpa.
我想见祖父
l want... Grandpa.
Don't you fret now.
别担心
Don't you fret now, Grandma.
别担心 祖母
- Everybody set back there? - Yeah.
- 都上车了吗？ - 上车了
Here we go.
好 我们出发
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
- Holy Moses, what a hard-looking outfit. - All them Okies is hard-looking.
- 天啊 这群人真顽强 - 俄基佬确实顽强
Boy, but l'd hate to hit that desert in ajalopy like that.
我是绝不会开这样一辆破车进沙莫的
You and me got sense. Them Okies got no sense and no feeling.
你我都有理智 俄基佬没有理智 没有感觉
They ain't human. No human being would live the way they do.
他们不是人类 人是不会这样生存的
A human being couldn't stand to be so miserable.
人类受不了这种痛苦
Just don't know any better, l guess.
他们只是没见识过更好的生活
What a place. How would you like to walk across it?
这个鬼地方 你想不想步行穿过这儿？
People done it. lf they could, we could.
有人试过 他们能行 我们也可以
Lots must have died, too.
很多人死在路上
Well, we ain't out of it yet.
我们还没出去
- This here's the desert. We're right in it. - l wish it was day.
- 我们在沙莫中间 - 我希望现在是白天
Tom said if it was day, it'd cut the gizzard right out of you.
汤姆说现在是白天 但沙莫把光都遮蔽了
l seen a picture once and there was bones everywhere.
我看过一张照片 到处是骨头
- Man bones? - Some, l guess. But mostly cow bones.
- 人骨头？ - 有些是吧 大部分是牛骨
l sure would like to see some of them man bones.
我倒想看看人骨头
Grandpa. l want Grandpa.
我想见爷爷
Yes. Now everything's going to be all right.
一切都会好起来的
We got to get across, Grandma. The family's got to get across.
我们必须穿过这里 祖母 我们必须穿过这里
Seems like we wasn't never doing nothing but moving. l'm tired.
好像我们除了赶路还是赶路 我累了
Women's always tired.
女人总是爱累
You ain't... you ain't sorry, are you, honey?
你不会后悔吧 亲爱的？
No, but...
不 但…
But you seen that advertisement in the Spicy Western Story magazine.
你记得"西部故事"杂志的广告
Don't pay nothing. Just send them the coupon and you're a radio expert.
一分钱不用 只要把赠券寄过去就可以成为无线通信员
Nice clean work.
多轻松的工作
But we can still do it, honey.
现在也行啊 亲爱的
l ought to done it then, not come on any trip like this.
我早就该这么做了 不该加入这个旅程
- What's this here? - Agricultural inspection.
- 什么事？ - 农业监察
We gotta go over your stuff. Got any vegetables or seed?
我们要例行检查 带蔬菜或种子了吗？
No.
没有
We gotta look over your stuff. You gotta unload.
我们得检查才行 卸车
Unload? Holy Moses.
什么 卸车？ 天啊
You'll have to get out while we unload for inspection.
抱歉 你们要先出来 我们要卸车检查
We got a sick old lady. We got to get her to a doctor. We can't wait. You can't make us wait.
先生 车上有病重的老人 必须找位医生 等不及了
Yeah? Well, we gotta look you over.
是吗？我们要检查
Well, l swear we ain't got anything. l swear it.
我发誓我们什么都没带 我发誓
Grandma's awful sick.
祖母病得很重
Look.
看
You wasn't fooling.
你没有撒谎
- You swear you got no fruit or vegetables? - No, l swear it.
- 你发誓车上没有水果蔬菜？ - 没有 我发誓
Go ahead. Get a doctor at Barstow. That's just eight miles.
那走吧 巴斯托有医生 离这儿8英里
But don't stop or get off. Understand?
不要停 不要下车 明白吗？
- OK, Cap. Much obliged. - Thanks.
- 谢谢 警官 - 非常感谢
Ma! Grandma! Look!
妈看
There she is. There she is. l never knowed there was anything like her.
到了 我从没见过这么漂亮的地方
- Will you look at her. - Look yonder, John.
-  看看 - 看看 约翰
Look how purdy and green it is, Winfield.
这里真漂亮 到处都是绿色
- Wonder if them's orange trees, John? - Look like orange trees to me.
- 是橘子树吗？ - 我看是
- They sure are pretty, whatever they are. - lndeed.
- 不管是什么树 真漂亮 - 确实
Look at them haystacks. l bet we sure could have fun playing over there.
看那里的草堆 肯定很好玩
Pretty, ain't it? Mighty pretty. Tom.
真漂亮
Where's Ma? l want Ma to see this. Look, Ma. Come here, Ma.
妈在哪儿？让她看看
Come on. Come on.
来啊 妈
- You sick, Ma? - You say we got across?
- 你不舒服？ - 我们到了吗？
Look.
看
Oh, thank God.
谢天谢地
And we're still together. Most of us.
我们大部分人还在一起
Didn't you sleep none?
你没睡觉吗？
- Was Grandma bad? - Grandma's dead.
- 祖母情况很糟吗？ - 祖母死了
When?
什么时候？
- Since before they stopped us last night. - That's why you didn't want them to look?
- 昨天我们被拦住前 - 所以你才不让他们检查？
l was afraid they'd stop us and we wouldn't get across.
我怕被他们拦下 就来不了这儿了
l told Grandma.
我跟祖母说她要死了
l told her when she was dying. l told her the family had to get across.
我跟她说我们必须得过去
l told her we couldn't take no chance on being stopped.
我们不能被拦住
So it's all right.
没关系
She'll get buried where it's nice and green, trees and flowers all around.
她可以葬在绿草茵茵的地方了 树木花草环绕着她
She got to lay her head down in California after all.
她最终还是死在加州了
Whoa.
太好了
How far you figure you going to get that way, pushing?
靠这么推着能走多远？
Right here. We run out of gas.
就到这儿 没油了
Where's the best place to get work around here? Don't matter what kind either.
哪里好找工作？ 什么工作都行
lf l've seen one of them things, l've seen 10,000 of 'em.
我见过无数张这样的广告了
- Why? Ain't it no good? - Not here. Not now.
- 不是真的吗？ - 这儿现在没有
There was some picking around here about a month ago, but it's all moved south.
一个月前有采摘潮 现在南移了
- What part of Oklahoma you from, anyhow? - Sallisaw.
- 你们从俄州哪里来？ - 沙拉索
Sallisaw? l come out from Cherokee County myself about two years ago.
沙拉索？ 我两年前从崔洛基郡来的
- Cherokee County! Gee! - Oh, boy!
- 崔洛基郡？不是开玩笑吧 - 噢
- Connie's folks are from Cherokee County. - You don't say!
- 康尼跟你是同乡 - 你不早说
All right, all right. Let's don't go into it.
好了不要闲扯了
What l gotta tell you is this: don't try to park in town tonight. Just go on out to that camp.
我得告诉你们 不要在城里停车 一直开到流民营
lf l catch you in town after dark l gotta lock you up.
如果天黑后被我撞到 就得把你关起来
- But what are we gonna do? - Well, pop, thatjust ain't up to me.
- 我们该怎么办呢？ - 这我就管不着了
l don't mind telling you the guy they ought to lock up is the guy that sent them things out.
不怕告诉你 该关起来的是那些乱发广告的人
How many, folks?
加多少油？
One.
一加仑
城界
前行2英里到流民营
Sure don't look none too prosperous.
这里不像什么繁华地
- Wanna go somewhere else? - On a gallon of gas?
- 想去别的地方吗？ - 就靠一加仑油？
Let's set up the tent and maybe l can fix some stew.
把帐蓬支起来 我来炖菜
l could break up some brush if you want me, ma'am.
我可以帮你掰树枝
- You wanna be asked to eat, don't you? - Yes, ma'am.
- 你想吃东西是吧？ - 是的 妈妈
- Didn't you have no breakfast? - No, ma'am. They ain't no work hereabouts.
- 没有吃早饭吗？ - 没有 这里没活儿干
Pa's been trying to sell some stuff to get gas, so as we can get along.
爸爸想变卖东西买油 去别的地方
Didn't none of these have no breakfast?
你也没吃早饭？
l did. Me and my brother did. We ate good.
我和我弟弟吃了 我们吃得很好
- Well, you ain't hungry then, are you? - We ate good.
- 那应该不饿才对 - 我们吃的很好
l'm glad some of you ain't hungry. There won't be enough to go all around.
有人不饿肚子就好 这里的东西也不够吃
Aw, he was braggin'. Know what he done?
他吹牛
Last night, come out and say they got chicken to eat.
昨晚他说吃了难
Well, l looked in whilst they was eating and it was fried dough, just like everybody else.
我偷看了一下 吃的是跟我们一样的烤面团
Ma? How about it?
太太 行吗？
Well, l don't know what to do. l've got to feed the family...
我不知道该怎么办 我家人也要吃饭
What am l gonna do about all these here?
这些孩子怎么办？
Give this to Ruthie.
拿给露西
There you are, John.
你的 约翰
Here, Tom. You take it. l ain't hungry.
汤姆 你吃吧 我不饿
- What do you mean? You ain't ate today. - l know, but l got a stomachache.
- 什么？你今天也没吃东西 - 我胃痛
l ain't hungry.
我不饿
- Take that plate in the tent and you eat it. - lt wouldn't be no use. l'd still see them.
- 把碟子拿进帐蓬吃 - 没用的 我开能看到他们
You get! Go on now. Get!
走 快走
You ain't doing no good. There ain't enough for you anyway.
没用的 反正也不够吃
Go on... now.
快走
You can't send them away.
赶不走他们
Here. Take your plates and go inside.
来 拿你们的碟子到里面吃
Now look, all you little fellas. You each go and get you a nice flat stick
孩子们 每人都去拿一块干净木板
and l'll put what's left for you. Huh?
我把剩下的菜分给你们
Now get.
快去
l don't know whether l'm doing right or not.
不知道我作的对不对
Get inside! Get inside, everybody, and stay inside!
都进去 呆在里面
Lady's gonna feed us. Get yourself a tin can.
去拿只罐头盒 太太要给我们吃的了
- Come on. Give me some. - You're taking too much.
- 快点儿 给我一些 - 你拿的太多了
You men wanna work?
你们想工作吗？
Sure we wanna work. Where's it at?
当然 在哪儿？
Tovaris County. Fruit's opening up. Need a lot of fruit pickers.
德瓦郡 水果成熟了 需要大量采果工
- You doing the hiring? - Well, l'm contracting the land.
- 你负责雇佣人吗？ - 我是那块地的承包商
- What you paying? - Well, can't tell exactly yet. 30 cents, l guess.
- 多少钱？ - 很难说 大概30美分
Why can't you tell? You took the contract, didn't you?
为什么不能确定？ 你不是承包商吗？
That's true, but it's keyed to the price.
对 这个价格有调整的余地
Might be a little more, might be a little less.
可高可低
All right, mister. l'll go.
好 我去
Just show us your licence to contract. Then you make out an order.
给我们看看你的承包执照 然后给个价钱
Where, when and how much you're gonna pay. You sign it and we'll go.
付费的时间地点 然后签名 我们就去
Now listen, smart guy. l'll run my business my own way.
听着 机灵鬼 我的生意我说了算
l got work. lf you want to take it, OK. lf not, just sit here, that's all.
我这里有活儿 想干就干 不想干就老实呆着
Twice now l've fell for that line.
我上了两次当了
Maybe he needs 1,000 men. So he gets 5,000 there and he'll pay 15 cents an hour.
或许只需要一千工人 但他招5000个 每小时只给15美分
You guys will have to take it because you'll be hungry.
饿着肚子的我们还不得不接受
lf he wants to hire, let him write it out and say what he's gonna pay.
想雇人的话就让他写清楚价钱
Ask to see his licence. He ain't allowed to contract men without a licence.
让他拿出执照 没有执照的话他不能雇人的
Hey, Joe.
乔
Agitator.
煽动者
- Ever see this guy before? - Seems like l have.
- 见过他吗？ - 好像见过
Seems like l seen him hanging around a used-car lot that was busted into.
他好像在失的车库附近转悠过
Yep, that's the fella. Get in this car.
就是他 上车来
- You got nothing on him. - Open your trap again and you'll go too.
- 你根本就无凭无据 - 再说一遍 连你也抓
You don't wanna listen to troublemakers. You better all pack and come to Tovaris County.
不要听这些捣乱分子的话 现在就收拾包袱跟我去德瓦郡
Come on, you.
过来
Give me that gun. Now get out of here. Go down to the willows and wait.
把枪给我 快跑 藏到树林里等着
- l ain't gonna run. - Why, the sheriff, he seen you, Tom.
- 我不会跑的 - 他是警长 他看到你了
You wanna get fingerprinted? You wanna be sent back for breaking parole?
难道你想再被采一次指纹？ 想在假释期被捉？
l guess you're right.
你说的不错
Hide in the willows. lf it's all right for you to come back, l'll give you four high whistles.
藏到树林里 没事的话 我会吹四声口哨
- What's going on here? - This man of yours, he got tough so l hit him.
- 什么事？ - 你的人发怒了 我打了他
Then he started shooting. Hit that woman there, so l hit him again.
他开枪打中了一位女士 我又打了他
What did you do in the first place?
你做什么了？
l talked back.
我顶嘴了而已
ls this the fella that hit you?
是他打了你？
- Don't look like him. - Oh, it was me all right.
- 好像是 - 当然是 你没错
You just got smart with the wrong fella.
你只是惹错了人
Get in that car.
带他上车
- This lady's bleeding to death. - Boy, what a mess them .45s make.
- 她会失血而死的 - 真是糟透了 45式子弹
Better get the doc.
去找医生
Al.
艾尔？
- You can come in now. - We gotta get out of here.
- 进来 汤姆 - 今晚我们要离开这儿？
Guy in the willows was telling me them pool room fellas figure on burning the camp out.
我在树林里听说弹子房的人今晚要烧掉流民营
We gotta get the truck loaded. Ma.
得马上把卡车装好 妈
Pa.
爸
- What are you doing with the jack handle? - Oh, she just got sassy, that's all.
- 你拿着千斤顶干吗 - 她生气了
Fight it out later. We got to hustle. Where's Connie?
等等再说这个 我们得抓紧 康尼去哪儿了？
Well, Tom, he's gone. He lit out this evening. Said he didn't know it was gonna be like this.
走了 他今晚走了 说没想到会这样
- Glad to get shot of him. Never was no good. - Pa! Shh!
- 走了正好 他从来没有也不会尽到责任 - 爸
How come l got to shh? Run out on us, didn't he?
我怎能忍得住？像这样弃我们而去
Cut it out, Pa. Help Al with the truck.
别说了 爸 帮艾尔装车
Some of the fellas in town, they gonna burn out the camp tonight.
有人今晚要烧掉流民营
Aw, don't fret, honey. You'll be all right.
别担心 亲爱的 你会好起来的
Tom, l just don't feel like nothing at all.
汤姆 我的生活毫无意意
Without him, l just don't want to live.
没了他 我不想活下去
He'll be back. We'll leave word for him.
他会回来的 我们会留言给他
Just don't you worry.
不要担心
Get on. Ma, you and Rosasharn climb up.
上来
Ma.
妈 可能…
Maybe... maybe Connie gone to get some books to study up with.
可能他只是去找书学习
He going to be a radio expert, you know.
他会成为无线电专家的
Maybe he figured to surprise us.
或许他只想给我们一个惊喜
Maybe that's just what he done.
或许他就是这么打算的
Ma, there comes a time when a man gets mad.
总有一天我会发疯的…
- You promised me... - l know, Ma. l'm trying to.
- 答应我不要那样 汤姆 - 我尽力吧
lf there was a law, maybe we could take it. But it ain't the law.
如果有法治的话 我们尚可接受 但这里是不法之地
They're working on our spirits, trying to make us cringe and crawl, working on our decency.
他们逼的我们像爬虫一般毁掉我们的尊严
- You promised, Tom. - l know. l'm trying to, Ma. Honest l am.
- 你答应过我 汤姆 - 我知道 我会尽力的 不骗你
You gotta keep clear. The family's breaking up. You gotta keep clear.
你得保持清醒 这个家要散了 你得保持清醒
What's that? A detour?
难道这里是便道？
- Tom! Tom! Please! - Tom!
- 汤姆 不要 - 汤姆
Just where do you think you're going?
你们要去哪儿？
We're strangers here, mister. We heard there was work in a place called Tovaris.
我们刚来这儿 先生 听说德瓦郡有活儿干
Yeah? You're heading the wrong way. What's more, we don't want more Okies in this town.
是吗？你走错路了 另外 这里不欢迎俄基佬
There ain't enough work here for them that's already here.
这里的活儿根本就不够
- Which way's it at? - You turn right around and head north.
- 哪边走 先生？ - 转右 往北走
And don't you come back until the cotton's ready. You understand?
棉花成熟之前不要回来 知道吗
Pa. Let's try that other tyre.
爸 我们试试另一个轮胎吧
- You got another flat tyre, Tom? - What? Another one?
- 轮胎又没气了 - 又有轮胎没气了？
Pa, get that spare back there?
爸爸 把毯子拿来
Ma, will you get the hell off there. This is gonna be heavy enough.
妈 站起来好吗？车已经够重的了
Tell you, something's got to happen soon.
必须得想个办法
We're down to our last day of grease and two days of flour and ten potatoes.
我们只剩下一天的黄油 两天的面粉…十只土豆
And Rosasharn - we gotta remember she's gonna be due soon.
还有罗丝 她快要临盆了
- Morning. - Morning.
- 早上好 - 早上好
- You folks looking for work? - We're looking even under boards for work.
- 在找工作吗？ - 我们找工作都快找疯了
- Can you pick peaches? - We can pick anything.
- 摘桃子有兴趣吗？ - 摘什么都行
There's plenty of work about 40 miles up here, this side of Pixley.
再走40英里 匹克雷旁边活儿多的是
You turn east on 32, look for the Keene ranch. Tell them Spencer sent you.
在32号公路转东 找基尼果园 说史先生介绍你们去的
- Mister, we sure thank you. - Thank you.
- 多谢 先生 - 多谢
Come on, Ma.
我们走 妈
- What is it? A wreck? - Where do you think you're going?
- 这是什么 失事车？ - 你们去哪儿？
Fella named Spencer sent us. Said there was work.
史先生介绍我们来的 说这里有摘桃子的活儿
- Oh, you wanna work, huh? - Sure do.
- 你们想工作对吧？ - 当然
All right. Just pull up in line there.
在前面排队
- OK for this one. Take 'em through. - What's the matter? What happened?
- 放他过去 带他进去 - 怎么回事？
Oh, a little trouble up there, but you'll get through all right.
出了点小麻烦 你没问题的
Go ahead.
到这边来
What do you think it is? A washout?
什么事 难道是大清洗？
l don't know what these cops have got to do with it, but l don't like it.
我不知道警察来这儿干什么 不过我不喜欢
These are our own people too. All of them. l don't like this.
他们都是自己人 我不喜欢这样
Get going. Stay in line.
继续 排队
Go ahead.
继续
What are you gonna do, scab?
你要做工贼吗？
Go on. Hurry up.
继续 快点儿
Come on, come on, come on.
快 快
Go on up there.
继续
Up the street there.
去前面那条街
Keep in line, up the street.
排好队 前面那条街
Hold it, bud.
跟紧点 伙计
- Wanna work? - Sure, but what is this?
- 要工作吗 - 当然 不过这里搞什么名堂
- None of your business. Name? - Joad.
- 没你的事 - 乔德
- How many men? - Four.
- 多少个男人？ - 四个
- Women? - Two.
- 女人？ - 两个
- Kids? - Two.
- 小孩？ - 两个
Can you all work?
都能工作吗？
- Sure, l guess so. - OK. House 63.
- 可以 - 好 去63号房
Wages, five cents a box. No bruised fruit.
工资金是一篮5美分 不许碰伤水果
Move along. You go to work right away.
快 你们得马上开始工作
Come on, honey.
快 亲爱的
- Name? - Joad.
- 姓名？ - 乔德
Say, what is all this here?
这里搞什么名堂？
- Joad. Not here. - Licence?
- 乔德？没有 - 执照？
Oklahoma EL204.
俄州 EL204
Don't check.
不匹配
Now, you look here. We don't want no trouble with you.
听好 我们不想找你麻烦
Just do your own work and mind your business and you'll be all right.
干你的活儿 少管闲事就行了
Sure do wanna make you feel at home here all right.
真实宾至如归
- We going to live here, Ma? - Why, sure.
- 我们要住这儿吗？ - 对
This won't be so bad once we get her washed out.
扫一扫还不错
l liked the tent better.
这里还不如帐蓬
This has got a floor.
至少有地板
Won't leak when it rains.
下雨不会漏
Here. This might come in handy.
拿着 或许有用
- Name? - Still Joad.
- 姓名？ - 还是乔德
- How many? - Six. You all go on.
- 多少人？ - 六个
Rosasharn and me will unload the truck.
你们都去 罗丝和我来卸车
- Any more of them hamburgers, Ma? - No, there ain't.
- 还有汉堡吗？妈妈 - 没有了
- You made a dollar. That's a dollar's worth. - Dollar's worth? That?
- 你赚一美元只能买那么多 - 一美元就这么点
They charge extra at that company store and there ain't no other place.
公司的内部商店收费贵 又没有其它店子
Well, l ain't full.
我没吃饱
Tomorrow you'll get in a full day's work and a full day's pay and then we'll all have enough.
明天你工作一整天 拿一天的工资金就够我们吃了
You wouldn't thinkjust reaching up and picking would get you in the back.
想不到摘水果也会腰酸背痛
Think l'll walk out and find out what all that fuss outside the gate was.
我去看看门口究竟怎么回事
- Anybody come with me? - No, l think l'll set awhile, then go to bed.
- 有人一起去吗？ - 不去 我睡觉了
Think l'll look around and see if l can't meet me a girl.
我去看看能不能碰上位姑娘
- Say, when l was your age, l... - Pa!
- 姑娘？我在你这个年纪时 - 爸
Working on me what all that yelling was about. Got me all curious.
我有些好奇 想看看门口究竟什么名堂
l'll be back in a little while.
我一会儿就回来
Tom. Now, you be careful. Don't you go sticking your nose in anything.
小心 汤姆 别惹麻烦
OK, Ma. Don't worry.
好 别担心
Where do you think you're going?
你去哪儿？
Thought l'd take a walk.
散步
- ls there any law against that? - You can just turn around and walk back.
- 法律规定不许散步吗 - 你最好往回走
- You mean l can't even get out of here? - Not tonight you can't.
- 我连到外面都不行吗？ - 今晚不行
Do you want to walk back? Or shall l whistle up some help and have you taken back?
要么你自己回去 要么我叫人来拖你回去
l'll walk back.
我自己回去
- Evening. - Who are you?
- 晚上好 - 你是谁？
- Just going past. - Know anybody around here?
- 只是路过 - 认识这儿的人吗？
No. Just going past, l tell you.
不认识 我说了我只是路过
- Casy! - Well, if it ain't Tom Joad. Hiya, boy.
- 凯西 - 汤姆·乔德 你好
- l thought you was in jail. - No. They just run me out of town.
- 我以为你坐牢了 - 没 他们只把我赶出了城
Come on in. Tom Joad.
进来 汤姆·乔德
- This the fella you been talking about? - That's him. What are you doing?
- 他就是你谈起过的好汉？ - 对 你在这儿干吗？
Working, picking peaches.
工作 摘桃子
l heard fellas shouting when we come in. l came to find out what's going on.
我们来时听到有人在喊叫 我来看看怎么回事
- What's it about? - This here's a strike.
- 究竟怎么了？ - 我们在罢工
Five cents a box ain't much, but a fella can eat.
5美分一桶不多 但够填饱肚子
- Five cents? They paying you five cents? - Sure. We made a buck since midday.
- 5美分？他们给你5美分？- 当然 从中午要现在我们赚了1美元了
Looky, Tom. We come here to work.
我们来这儿找工
They tell us it's gonna be five cents, but there's a whole lot of us.
起初说好5美分 后来因为人太多
So the man says two and a half cents.
他们把价格压到2.5美分
A fella can't even eat on that and if he's got kids...
连肚子都吃不饱 如果有孩子的话…
So we says we won't take it.
我们不肯接受
So they drive us off. Now they're paying you five cents.
他们把我们赶了出来 现在他们付给你们5美分
Dunno. Paying five now.
现在是5美分
They'll get two and a half cents just the minute we're gone.
我们一离开就会变成2.5美分
You know what that is.
就是说
One ton of peaches, picked and carried for a dollar.
一吨桃子 又要摘又要抬 才一美元
That way you can't even buy enough food to keep you alive.
连肚子都填不饱
Tell 'em to come out with us, Tom. Them peaches is ripe.
号召大家跟我们一起罢工 他们的桃子再不摘就迟了
Two days out and they'll pay us all five. Maybe seven.
罢工持续两天 他们就会让步 给我们5甚至7美分
They won't. They're getting five now. That's all they care about.
不 他们已经满足于现在的5美分了 这就是他们所关心的
But the moment they ain't strike-breaking, they won't get no five.
但总有一天拿不到5美分的
Next thing you know you'll be out. They got it all fixed down to a T.
然后就会赶你出来 他们早就计划好了
Soon as the harvest is in you're a migrant worker. Afterwards, just a bum.
收获季节一到 你就是移民工人 之后 你就是流民
Five they're getting now. That's all they're interested in.
他们关心的是现在的5美分
l know what Pa would say. He'd say it's none of his business.
我知道爸会怎么说 "这不关他的事"
That's right. He'll have to take a beating before he'll know.
不 他得吃点亏才会明白
Take a beating? We was out of food.
吃亏？我们没吃的了
Tonight we had meat - not much, but we had it.
今晚我们吃了肉 尽管不多 但总算是吃了
You think Pa's gonna give up his meat on account of some other fellas?
爸是不会为了其它人放弃饱饭的
Rosasharn needs milk.
罗丝需要奶水
You think Ma's gonna starve that baby just on account of fellas yelling outside a gate?
妈也不会为了门外抗议的人群让婴儿饿死
Tom, you gotta learn like l'm learning.
汤姆 你终究会像我一样明白的
l don't know what's right yet myself, but l'm trying to find out.
我不知道对不对 但我想知道
That's why l can't ever be a preacher again.
所以我当不了牧师
Preacher's got to know.
牧师必须了解一切
l don't know.
我不了解
l got to ask.
我去问问
- l don't like it. - What's the matter?
- 不好 - 怎么回事？
l can't tell. Seems as though l hear something and when l listen there ain't nothing to hear.
不知道 我好像听到什么声音 但仔细听又好像没什么
lt ain't out of the Question, you know.
这没什么异常的
Cops been telling us how they gonna beat us up and run us out.
他们不是警察
Not them regular deputies, but them tin-seal men. The ones they got for guards.
只是这里的治安员
They figure l'm the leader cos l talk so much.
我说话太多 他们以为我是领袖
Turn out the light. Come outside. There's something here.
关了灯 出来 这里有什么东西
- What is it? - l don't know. Listen.
- 怎么了？ - 不知道 听
- Can't tell whether you hear it or not. - You hear it, Tom?
- 不知道听到没有 - 汤姆 你听到没有？
l hear it. l think there's some guys coming this way. A lot of 'em.
听到了 好像有不少人朝这边走来
- We gotta get outta here. - Down that way! Under the bridge span.
- 我们得赶紧离开 - 那边走 去桥下
(man) There he is! The one in the middle. The skinny one. Chuck! Alec! Get him!
是他 中间那个瘦子抓住他
You don't know what you're doing! You're helping starve kids.
听着 你不知道自己在做什么
- Aw, shut up, you dirty... - Casy!
- 你在为虎作伥 会饿死孩子的 - 住嘴 混蛋
- You've killed him! - Serves him right too.
- 他死了 - 活该
Look out!
小心
- Boy, he's dead. He's good and dead. - Did you see the fella that done it?
他死了 看到谁打死他了吗？
l ain't sure, but l caught him across the face, a trademark he won't get rid of in a hurry.
不确定 但我打到了他的脸 脸上有记号 他跑不了的
Ma?
妈？
Tom! Tom! Pa, wake up. Al, get the light.
汤姆 老头子 快起来 艾尔 开灯
- Anybody ask anything? - No, ma'am.
- 有人问什么吗？ - 没有 妈
- Well, you stay by that door. - Yes, ma'am.
- 在门口守着 - 是 妈妈
Tommy?
汤米
How's it feel?
感觉怎么样？
Busted my cheek, but l can still see.
我的脸破了 但还能看到东西
- What did you hear? - Looks like you've done it.
- 你听到什么风声了？ - 你还是惹麻烦了
l thought so. Felt like it.
我想是的 好像是这样
Folks ain't talking about much else.
大家都在谈昨晚的事
They say they got posses out.
他们说有人秘密集会
Talking about a lynching when they catch the fella.
说逮到那人肯定要好好修理他
They killed Casy first.
他们先打死凯西
That ain't the way they're telling it. They're saying you done it first.
他们可不是这么说的 他们说是你先动手
Do they know...
他们知道…
what the fellow looks like?
那人长什么样吗？
They know he got hit in the face.
他们知道他脸上受伤了
l'm sorry, Ma.
抱歉 妈
l didn't know what l was doing any more than when you take a breath.
你一叹气 我都不知道该怎么办
l didn't even know l was going to do it.
我不知道会打死人
Oh, it's all right, Tommy.
没事 汤米
l wished you didn't do it.
我希望你没打死人
But you done what you had to do.
但你也没办法
And l can't read no fault in you.
错不在你
l'm going away tonight. l can't go putting this on you.
我今晚离开了 我不能连累你们
Tom.
汤姆
There's a whole lot l don't understand.
许多事我不明白
But going away ain't going to ease us.
但你走掉我们也不会轻松
There was a time we was on the land.
以前我们有块土地
There was a boundary to us then.
有一块边界
Old folks died off and little fellas come...
老人死去 新人出世
We was always one thing.
我们始终是一体
We was the family.
我们是一家人
Kind of whole and clear.
清白完整的一家人
But now we ain't clear no more.
现在我们不再清白了
They ain't nothing that keeps us clear.
我们再也清白不了
Al, he's hankering and gibbeting to be off on his own.
艾尔整天只顾着自己
Uncle John's just dragging around.
约翰叔叔只是得过且过
Your pa's lost his place. He ain't the head no more.
你父亲不再是一家之主
We're cracking up, Tom.
这个家零散了 汤姆
There ain't no family now.
我们已经没有家了
And Rosasharn, she's gonna have her baby, but it won't have no family.
罗丝就要生孩子 生出来就是个没家的孩子
l been trying to keep her going, but...
我想鼓励她 可…
And Winfield.
还有文菲尔德
What's he gonna be this way?
这样下去他会变成什么样呢？
Growing up wild, and Ruthie too.
跟露西像野孩子一样长大
Just like animals.
跟畜生一样
Got nothing to trust.
无可信任
Don't go, Tom.
不要走 汤姆
Stay and help.
留下帮忙吧
Help me.
帮我的忙
OK, Ma. l shouldn't, l know l shouldn't, but OK.
好 妈妈 我不该这样 但没关系
Ma, here come a lot of people.
妈妈 来了好多人
- (man) How many? - Ten of us.
- 多少 - 10个
House 25. The number's on the door.
25号房 房号在门上
- OK, mister. What you paying? - Two and a half cents.
- 先生 这里薪水多少？ - 2.5美分
Two and a half? Say, mister, a man can't make his dinner on that.
2.5美分？ 这么点钱连肚子都填不饱
Take it or leave it. There are 200 men coming in from the South will be glad to get it.
不想干就算了 南方还有200个人赶着来做呢
- But how are we gonna eat? - Look...
- 我们怎么才能吃饱饭呢？ - 听着
l didn't set the price. lf you want it, OK. lf you don't, turn around and beat it.
想干就留下 不想干就走人
- Which way to house 25? - Straight up the street.
- 去25号房怎么走？ - 一直向前
That Casy.
凯西
He might have been a preacher, but he seen things clear.
他是做过牧师 不过他看的最透撤
He was like a lantern.
他就像一盏明灯
He helped me to see things too.
让我也明白起来
Comes night, we'll get out of here.
今晚我们一起走
Like a lantern.
就像一盏明灯
- l'll start the car. - Yes.
- 我去把车发动起来 - 好的
All right, Tom.
好了 汤姆
Jump up. Jump up.
上来
Just till we get distance. Then you can come out.
我们走一段路你就出来
l'd hate to get trapped in here.
或许是困在这里
Get in, Ma.
上来 妈
- (man) Hey! Where you going? - We're going out.
- 来 约翰 你们去哪儿？ - 我们要走
- What for? - We got ajob offered. A good job.
- 为什么？ - 我们找到了工作 一份好工作
Yeah?
是吗？
Well, let's take a look at you.
我们查查看
- Wasn't there another fella with you? - You mean that hitchhiker?
- 还有人吗？ - 你是说那个搭便车的？
- Little short fella with a pale face? - l guess that's what he looked like.
- 小个子 白脸那个？ - 差不多吧
We just picked him up on the way in.
我们进来时他才爬上车
- He left when the rate dropped. - What did you say he looked like again?
- 今早减工资金时他就走了 - 他长什么样子？
Short fella. Pale face.
小个子 白脸
Was he bruised about the face this morning?
今早他脸上有伤疤吗？
l didn't see nothing.
我没看到
OK, go on.
好 走吧
- Going out for good? - Yeah. Going north. Got ajob.
- 不回来了 - 对 我们在北边找到了工作
OK.
好
- Done good, Al. You done real good. - Know where we're going?
- 你真行 艾尔 - 我们去哪儿？
lt don't matter. We got to go and keep going till we get plenty of distance away from here.
去哪儿都没关系 我们先得远远离开这儿
Ouch! She's hotter than a heifer.
天啊 烫手
- What's up? - The fan belt's shot.
- 怎么了？ - 风扇皮带坏了
Sure picked a nice place for it too, didn't she?
坏的真是地方
- Got any gas? - About half a gallon.
- 还有油吗？ - 大约半加仑
Well, Ma, sure looks like we done her this time.
这次它真的不行了
Lights up ahead. That might be a camp or something.
前面有灯光 可能是营地
Looks like about a mile. Reckon she'll coast her, Al?
有一英里 车能开到哪儿吗？
- Got to coast it. - Well, let's give her a whirl. Huh?
开不到也不行 来 推推车
Come on, kids. Get in. John!
来 孩子们 上车约翰
农业部：农民临时营
Did you hurt yourself, John?
摔到了吗 约翰？
No.
没
- You hit it too fast. - What's the idea of that?
- 你刹车太猛了 - 什么意思？
Well, you see a lot of children play in here.
这里好多孩子玩
You can tell people to drive slow and they're liable to forget,
我常提醒司机减速 可他们总是忘
but once they hit that hump they don't forget.
撞到这土丘 他们就不忘了
- Got any room here for us? - You're lucky.
- 这里有位子吗 - 你们算走运了
How do you do, ma'am? How are you?
你好 太太
How are you?
你好
Down that line, turn to the left. You'll see it. You'll be in number four sanitary unit.
一直走下去 转左就能看到 你们住在第四卫生组
- What's that? - Toilet, showers, washtubs.
- 什么？ - 洗手间 浴室 洗衣房
We'll have washtubs with running water?
这里有洗衣房和自来水？
Yes, ma'am.
对
Camp committee will call on you in the morning, get you fixed.
流民营委员会早上会拜访并安置你们
- Cops? - No. No cops.
- 警察？ - 不
No, people here elect their own cops. The ladies' committee'll call on you, ma'am.
妇女委员会将会联系你
Tell you about the children, the schools and sanitary unit and who takes care of 'em.
谈谈儿童管理 教育和卫生和谁负责照顾孩子
Will you come inside and sign up?
你进来签个名好吗？
Drive her on down, Al. l'll sign up.
把车开过去 我来签名
Right this way. ln here.
这边
Now, l don't want to seem inQuisitive, you understand,
我不想问东问西
but there's certain information l have to have. What's your name?
但有些东西我一定要知道 你叫什么？
Joad. Tom Joad.
汤姆·乔德
- J-O... - A-D.
乔…德
And how many of you?
你们一共多少人？
Eight. Now.
现在有…8个
- Uncle John, you don't look so good. - l ain't so good, but l'm coming.
- 约翰叔叔 你看起来脸色不好 - 是不太好 不过我也要去
Shove.
推
Camp site costs a dollar a week. You can work that out
流民营一个星期收费1美元 但你可以打工补偿
carrying garbage, keeping the camp clean, things like that.
倒垃圾 搞卫生什么的
We'll work it out.
我们会工作的
What's the committee you're talking about?
你们谈的委员会是什么？
We have five sanitary units. Each one elects a central committee man.
我们共分五个卫生车位 每个选出一位委员
They make the laws and what they say goes.
制定法规 实施法规
You aiming to tell me the fellas running the camp are just fellas camping here?
难道你是说管理流民营的也是这里的流民？
- That's the way it is. - And you say no cops?
- 没错 - 没有警察？
No cop can come in here without a warrant.
没有许可证 警察不能进这里
l can't hardly believe it.
真不敢相信
Camp l was in before, they burnt it out. Deputies and some of them pool-room fellas.
我以前呆的流民营被烧掉了 放火的是警长和联防队员
They don't get in here. Sometimes the boys patrol the fences.
他们管不了这儿的
- Especially on dance nights. - You got dances too?
- 舞会时他们会在附近巡逻 - 这里还有舞会？
We have the best dances in the county, every Saturday night.
每个星期六晚上都有盛大的舞会
- Who runs this place? - The government.
- 是谁管理这里的？ - 政府
- Why ain't there more like it? - You find out. l can't.
- 为什么他们不学学政府 - 你问我？我也不知道
ls there anything like work around here?
这里有工作吗？
l can't promise you that, but there'll be a licensed agent here later if you want to talk.
这个我不敢保证 等下会有个拿执照的代理商 你跟他谈谈
That cut you have?
你的伤口…
- Crate fell on me. - You'd better take care of it.
- 箱子砸的 - 你最好处理一下它
Store manager will give you something for it. See you later.
店老板会帮你找些药 回见
Ma's sure going to like it here.
妈妈肯定会喜欢这里
She ain't been treated decent for a long while.
她好久没有过这样尊重的待遇了
See you later.
再见
请关好水龙头 保持营地清洁
- Winfield. l got something to show you. - What's the matter?
- 文菲尔德 起来 有东西给你 - 什么
lt's some white things made out of dish stuff, like in the catalogues. Come on, l'll show you.
有些白色的东西 跟商品目录里的一样 快 快来看
Come on. Ain't nobody going to say anything.
快 没人会骂我们的
There's where you wash your hands.
这里是洗手的地方
- What's these? - l reckon you stand in them little rooms.
- 这是什么？ - 站在小隔间里…
And water comes down out of that little jigger up there. You take a bath.
水就会从上面的水龙头流出来供我们洗澡
- Oh, look. Just like in the catalogues. - Hey! Don't you go a-monkeyin'!
- 看 跟商品目录里的一样 - 不要调皮
Now you done it! You busted it!
你把它弄坏了
All l done was pull that string.
我只不过是拉了那条线
- Hiya, Mr Thomas. - Morning.
- 汤姆斯 - 早上好
Morning.
早上好
Nice job.
干的好
Listen here. Maybe l'm going to talk myself out of my farm, but l like you fellas.
听着 我或许会放弃这农场 但我喜欢你们
You're good workers. So l'm going to tell you.
你们是好工人 我得告诉你们
- You live over in the government camp? - Yes, sir.
- 你们住在政府的流民营对吧？ - 是的
- You have dances there every Saturday night. - We sure do.
- 你们每个星期六晚都有舞会 - 没错
- Well, look out next Saturday night. - What's the matter?
- 下个星期六晚要留心 - 什么事？
l'm head to the central committee. l got to know.
我是那儿的头 我得知道
Well, don't tell l told you.
别说我告诉你们
Listen.
听着
"Citizens angered at red agitators burning other sQuatters' camps
愤怒的红色煽动者烧掉了另一座流民营
and order agitators to leave the county."
并命令煽动者离开该郡
Listen. What is these reds anyway?
红色煽动者是谁？
Every time you turn around somebody's calling somebody else a red.
你一转身 别人就把你说成红色
- What is these reds anyway? - l ain't talking about that, one way or another.
- 他们究竟是什么人？ - 我不会乱说的
All l'm saying is there's going to be a fight at the camp, Saturday night.
营里周末舞会时会出现打架事件
And there'll be deputies ready to go in.
警长会候在外面
Now go on with your work.
继续干活吧
Maybe l've talked myself into trouble, but you're folks like us and l like you.
或许我已经自找麻烦了 但你们是我的朋友 我喜欢你们
We won't tell who told. Thank you.
我们不会说出去的 谢谢
- All right. - There ain't gonna be no fight either.
- 好 - 架也不会打起来的
( ''She'll be Comin'Round the Mountain'')
（"她会从山边来"演奏）
- Evening. Who did you say invited you? - Mr and Mrs Brown.
- 晚上好 谁邀请你们的 - 布朗夫妇
Oh, go right on in, folks. Go right on in. Hello, there.
进来 兄弟们
Hi, Miz Jennings. How are you? Glad to see you.
你好 津宁先生 幸会
让这位淑女转啊转
让漂亮的姑娘转啊转
让那位姑娘转啊转
转啊…
让那位漂亮可爱的姑娘转起来？
- Hello. - Hello.
- 你好 - 你好
- Going to the dance tonight? l can waltz. - Oh, that's nothing. Anybody can waltz.
- 跳舞吗？我会华尔 - 这有什么 每个人都会华尔兹
- Not like me they can't. - You get going!
- 谁说的 他们不会 - 走开
This girl's spoke for. She's gonna be married and her man's coming for her. So get!
她已定亲了 要嫁人了 她男人就快来了 走开
Hiya, Bill. Nice-looking girl you got there.
你抱的姑娘真漂亮 比尔
- Howdy, Mr Thomas, Mrs Thomas. - Watching out, ain't you?
- 你好 托马斯先生 托马斯太太 - 你们在放风
- Don't worry. There ain't gonna be no trouble. - l hope you know what you're talking about.
- 别担心 不会有麻烦的 - 你最好说话小心点
Evenin', boys. Who did you say invited you?
晚上好 谁请你来的？
Fella named Jackson. Buck Jackson.
巴克杰克逊
- OK. Have a good time. - Thanks.
- 哦 玩的开心 - 谢谢
- Them's our fellas. - How do you know?
- 就是他们 - 你怎么知道？
Well...
这个…
Just got a feeling.
直觉而已
They're kind of scared too.
他们看起来战战兢兢
Follow 'em. Get hold of Jackson. See if he knows them. l'll stay here.
跟住他们盯紧杰克逊 看他们认识不 我呆在这儿
- Hello. - Hello.
- 你好 - 你好
So long.
再见
How do you do, Miz Joad?
你好吗 乔德太太？
My, you sure look pretty.
很好 你看起来真漂亮
- Please to dance? - Thank you kindly, but she ain't well.
- 去跳舞吧 - 多谢 但她感觉不会
- Sort of poorly. - Thank you just the same.
- 有些不舒服 - 不过还是谢谢你了
Howdy do.
你好？
Hey, Jackson.
杰克逊
Look. Did you ever see them fellas before?
你认识那帮人吗？
Sorry, neighbour, but we got to keep the camp clean.
抱歉 我们要保持营里的卫生
l know one of 'em. Used to work with him. l never asked him to the dance though.
认识一个 以前我们是工友 但我没有邀请他来舞会
All right. Keep your eye on 'em. Just keep 'em in sight, that's all.
好 盯住他就行了
l seen them. A car with five men parked down by the eucalyptus trees.
一辆车停在桉树旁 上面有五个人
And another with four men on the main road, and they got guns. l seen 'em.
另有一辆在公路上 全部带了枪 我看到了
Thank you, Willy. You done right good. You can run along and dance now.
谢谢 威里 干的好 去跳舞吧
Well, sure looks like the fat's in the fire this time.
看来这次是非干不可了
What them deputies wanna hurt the camp for? How come they can't let us alone?
治安员怎么和营地过不去 怎么不让我们安稳
- We ought to get some pickaxe handles... - No. That's just what they want.
- 我们去拿几支铁镐和… - 不 他们正希望如此
No, sirree. lf they can get a fight going they can call in the cops. Say we ain't orderly.
如果这里打起来 他们就能叫警察来维和
- They're here. We got 'em spotted. - Everything ready?
- 他们来了 - 准备好了吗？
- There ain't gonna be trouble. - l don't want you hurting them.
- 不会有麻烦的 - 不要伤害他们
Don't worry. Everything's arranged. Maybe nobody will see it.
不用担心 一切都安排好了 不会有人发觉
Well, just don't use no sticks or no knives or no piece of iron.
不要用棍棒 刀子 或铁器
lf you gotta sock 'em, sock 'em where they ain't going to bleed.
要打就打那些不会流血的部位
Gentlemen, hats off please. Thank you.
先生们 请脱帽 谢谢
（演奏"红河谷"）
- She's getting purdier every day, Ma. - Girl with a baby's always purdier.
- 她一天比一天漂亮 妈 - 要生孩子的姑娘只会更漂亮
- Come on, Ma, let's dance. - Oh, Tom. l can't.
- 来吧 妈 我们来跳舞 - 汤姆 我…
Well, all right.
好 好
Tom, stop.
汤姆 停下
Come and sit by my side if you love me
如果你爱我 请坐下来陪我
Do not hasten to bid me adieu
不要急着离开我
But remember the Red River Valley
记住红河谷
And the boy who had loved you so true
和那真心爱你的男孩
9.29. Let's go!
九点二十九 上
All right. 9.30. Here we go.
九点半 我们出发
- All right. l'll dance with her. - You and who else?
- 让开 我来和她跳舞 - 你和谁跳舞？
Excuse me, Ma.
失陪 妈妈
Open up! We're here about a riot!
开门这里有骚乱
- Riot? l don't see any riot. Who are you? - Deputy sheriffs.
- 骚乱？我没看到什么骚乱 你是谁？ - 副警长
- You got a warrant? - We don't need a warrant when there's a riot.
- 你有许可证吗？ - 暴乱的时候不用许可证
l don't know what you're going to do about it. l don't hear or see any riot.
我不知道你想做什么 我可不知道什么骚乱
What's more, l don't believe there is any riot. Look for yourself.
另外 我根本就不信有什么骚乱 自己看看
（演奏"草堆中的火难"）
All right, let's go.
好 我们走
(man) Oklahoma... EL204.
俄克拉荷马
You have no right to arrest without a warrant.
没有许可证的话你谁也不能逮捕
We'll have a warrant just as soon as we check with headQuarters.
跟总部打个招呼我们就可以拿到许可证
Tommy.
汤米
Ain't you gonna tell me goodbye?
你不跟我道个别吗？
l didn't know, Ma.
妈 我不知道…
l didn't know if l ought to.
我该不该走
- (Ruthie) Ma... - Hush, Ruthie.
- 妈 - 露西…
Come outside.
出去说
There was some cops here tonight. They was taking down licence numbers.
今晚有警察来过 他们在查车牌照
l guess somebody knows something.
他们肯定收到了风声
l guess it had to come. Sooner or later.
我早晚都要走
Sit down for a minute.
坐下
l'd like to stay, Ma.
我想留下来 妈
l'd like to be with you and see your face when you and Pa get settled in some nice place.
我想跟你在一起看着你和爸找个好地方安顿下来
l'd sure like to see you then.
我真希望这样
But l won't never get that chance, l guess now.
但我现在没这个机会了
- l could hide you, Tommy. - l know you would, but l ain't gonna let you.
- 我把你藏起来 汤米 - 我知道 但我不让你那么做
You hide somebody that's killed a guy and you're in trouble too.
我是杀人犯 包庇我你也会有麻烦的
All right, Tommy.
好 汤米
But what do you figure you're going to do?
你想去做什么？
You know what l've been thinking about?
你猜我在想什么？
About Casy.
我想起凯西
About what he said.
他说的话
What he done.
他做的事
About how he died.
他是怎么死的
And l remember all of it.
我每个细节都记得
He was a good man.
他是个好人
l've been thinking about us too.
我也在想
About our people living like pigs and good, rich land laying fallow.
我们过着牛马不如的生活 那些懒惰的富人
Or maybe one guy with a million acres and 100,000 farmers starving.
一个人可能就拥有几万顷地 而成千上万的农民却将要饿死
And l've been wondering if...
我在想是否…
all our folks got together and yelled...
我们能团结起来抗议
No. They'd drive you out and cut you down.
汤米 他们会像对凯西一样…
- Just like they done to Casy. - They're gonna drive me anyways.
- 对付你的 - 他们早晚会对付我的
Sooner or later they'd get me, for one thing if not for another.
早晚都会有罪名抓我的
Till then...
在那之前
Tommy.
汤米
- You're not aiming to kill nobody? - No, Ma. Not that. That ain't it.
- 你不会杀人吧？ - 不 不是
lt's just...
只是…
Well, as long as l'm an outlaw anyways, maybe l can do something.
只要我还是罪犯 或许我能做点什么
Maybe l can just find out something.
发现些什么
Just... scrounge around and maybe find out what it is that's wrong.
四处搜寻…或许能找到方法
Then see if they ain't something that can be done about it.
来改变现在的一切
l ain't thought it all out clear, Ma. l...
我还没想清楚 妈 我…
l can't. l don't know enough.
我不能 我了解的不够多
How am l gonna know about you, Tommy?
我怎么才能得知你的消息呢 汤米？
Why, they could kill you and l'd never know. They could hurt you. How am l gonna know?
如果他们杀了你 我却不知道 他们伤害你 我却不知道
Well, maybe it's like Casy says.
或许像凯西说的
Fella ain't got a soul of his own, just... a little piece of a big soul.
一个人的灵魂不只属于自己 它只是大灵魂的一小部分
The one big soul that belongs to everybody.
属于每个人的大灵魂
Then...
然后…
- Then what, Tom? - Then it don't matter.
- 然后怎样 汤米？ - 一个人的灵魂没什么关系
l'll be all around in the dark.
我在黑暗中无处不再
l'll be everywhere.
你目光所及…
Wherever you can look.
都是我
Wherever there's a fight so hungry people can eat, l'll be there.
哪里的穷人为吃饱肚子而抗争 哪里就有我
Wherever there's a cop beating up a guy, l'll be there.
哪里有警察殴打穷人 哪里就有我
l'll be in the way guys yell when they're mad.
我就在愤怒呼喊的人群中
l'll be in the way kids laugh when they're hungry and they know supper's ready.
我就在孩子们闻到晚饭香而欢笑的时候
And when people are eating the stuff they raise...
人们能够享用自己的粮食
living in the houses they build...
住进靠双手建造的家中时
l'll be there too.
我就在其中
l don't understand it, Tom.
我不明白 汤姆
Me neither, Ma, but...
我也不太明白
just something l've been thinking about.
这只是我的想法
Give me your hand, Ma.
把手给我 妈
Goodbye.
再见
Goodbye, Tommy.
再见 汤米
Later, when this is blowed over,
这一切都过去后
you'll come back.
你会回来吗？
Sure, Ma.
当然
Tommy, we ain't the kissing kind, but...
汤米 我们平时不接吻 不过…
Goodbye, Ma.
再见 妈
Goodbye, Tommy.
再见 汤米
Tommy...
汤米
Goodbye.
再见
Turn that up, Al, and get her rolled up.
快点 把车发动起来
- How you fixed, John? - Getting along.
- 好了吗 约翰 - 没什么问题
Here.
拿着
Winfield, get on top, out of the way.
文菲尔德 你到顶上去 让开路
l don't see what you folks are hurrying so for. They tell me there's 20 days' work up there.
这么急干什么 听说有20天的活
Yes, sir, and we aim to get in all 20 of them.
对 我们打算20天全赶上
- All ready, Ma? - Yes. How you feeling, Rosasharn?
- 准备好了没 妈 - 嗯 感觉怎样 罗丝
All aboard, everybody. All aboard for Fresno.
都上车 我们去弗雷斯诺
Wait a minute. l'll give you a hand.
等等 我来帮忙
- Careful of her, now. - Easy, child.
- 小心 - 放松 孩子
She'll be all right.
她会好起来的
- Watch her, John. - l'll take care of her.
- 照顾好她 约翰 - 没问题
- How are you fixed, Al? - All right, Pa.
- 准备好了没 艾尔？ - 好了 爸爸
Now, Ma.
妈
- Goodbye. - Goodbye.
- 再见 - 再见
- Thanks a lot. Goodbye. - Goodbye.
- 再见 多谢 - 再见
Thanks, Mr Conway.
多谢
- Bye. - You be careful.
- 再见 - 保重
20 days work. Oh, boy!
20天的工作 太好了
l'll be glad to get my hands on some cotton. That's the kind of picking l understand.
我真想摘棉花 摘棉花我最在行
Maybe. Maybe 20 days' work and maybe no days' work.
或许有20天的活 或许一天也没有
- We ain't got it till we get it. - What's the matter, Ma? Getting scared?
- 没到手之前什么也不能说 - 怎么了 妈？你害怕了？
Scared. Huh!
害怕
l ain't never gonna be scared no more.
我再也不会害怕了
l was though. For a while it looked as though we was beat. Good and beat.
有那么一刻 似乎我们被打倒了
Looked like we didn't have nobody in the world but enemies.
仿佛这个世界全是敌人
Like nobody was friendly no more.
再没有好心人了
Made me feel kind of bad and scared too.
我确实觉得伤心害怕
Like we was lost and nobody cared.
好像我们失败了 没有人关心我们
You're the one that keeps us going, Ma.
你是我们的支柱
l ain't no good no more and l know it.
我知道自己没用
Seems like l spend all my time these days thinking how it used to be.
我整天沉浸在回忆之中
Thinking of home.
想家
l ain't never gonna see it no more.
我再也见不到家了
Well, Pa, a woman can change better than a man.
老头子 女人的适应性比男人要好
A man lives sort of, well, in jerks.
男人的生活是跳跃式的
Baby's born or somebody dies, and that's ajerk.
孩子出生 或有人过世 这是个跳跃
He gets a farm or loses it, and that's ajerk.
获得或失去一间农场 也是个跳跃
With a woman it's all in one flow like a stream.
但女人的生活像溪流
Little eddies and waterfalls, but the river, it goes right on.
小的起伏不断 但水流不会停止
A woman looks at it that way.
女人是这样看世界的
- Well, maybe, but we're sure taking a beating. - l know.
- 可能吧 我们确实失败了 - 我知道
That's what makes us tough.
因此我们才更坚强
Rich fellas come up, and they die, and their kids ain't no good and they die out.
富人很快就销声匿迹 富家子弟也难以持久
But we keep coming. We're the people that live.
但我们永远不会灭绝 我们是人民
They can't wipe us out. They can't lick us.
消灭不了 打败不了
We'll go on forever, Pa, cos we're the people.
我们永远不会灭绝 因为 我们就是人民